When  working with spreadsheets,
there may be occasions where you need
to have that information sorted in a
specific format, such as alphabetically,
by date or numerical value.
The easiest way to do that
within spreadsheets is to
use the sort and filter tool.
And as you can see I have some
information in this sample spreadsheet
in front of me, and I'm just going to
demonstrate how you can apply some sort
and filter options to the information.
So the first thing we're going
to do is we're going to sort the
information alphabetically by country.
So if I just click on A and
it highlights all of column A.
And I'm on the home tab.
So if I then just go up to the sort
and filter tool in the top right-hand
corner and select the little drop
down there and I can sort, it, it
A to Z, Z to A or custom sort and
I'm simply going to sort it A to Z.
Now, once I've done that, Excel
has given me a warning message.
And the reason it's doing that is
that is other information that is
linked to the data within column A.
So it's asking me, do I want to
include that data, which is yes.
Otherwise that won't be a true reflection
of what was sent to the USA or Brazil.
So I'll tick the expand the selection
button and select sort, and that
automatically sorts everything
alphabetically, but all of the
information has been sorted as well.
It may be a case that you wish
to sort something by date.
And again, if I select column D
and select sort oldest to newest, I
will still get the warning message
because it needs to know that.
Do I want to include this information
or do I just sort the day column?
If I did that, this information
would no longer be accurate because
it would not link up with the dates.
So yes, I do want to expand the selection.
Select sort, and it will sort
everything on date value.
As well as using the sort tool, Excel also
has the filter tool, which allows you to
filter information so you can look for
specific elements within that information.
Again, this is on the sort and filter tab.
So what I need to do is I'm going
to select country and I'm going to
click on the filter button, and that
will apply some filters to the top.
So as you can see, there are now dropdown
icons next to the text on row one.
So if I click on the little dropdown,
this gives me the filter option, so
I can now select all, or if it was a
case that I needed to find out which
items were sold to certain countries.
So I would just untick that.
And I'll just for example, select
three of these and select OK.
And those are the countries
so it hides everything else.
And I'm only seeing information
relating to what was sold in
Angola, Bulgaria and Cameroon.
Excel identifies that there is
a filter applied by giving the
filter icon in the top corner.
So just so you're aware if you
needed to clear that you can
select clear filter from country
and it will all go back to normal.
So at a  glance, you could tell whether
there was a filter applied or not.
If the filter icon was highlighted
in any of the column headings.
So for this one, what I'm going to do, I'm
just going to demonstrate again, I've got
item type here, so I just need to see what
was sold, beverages, cereal and clothes.
And I can apply other filters so
I may need to know, which was sold
online, which was sold offline.
So I'll just select online,
so I've ticked offline.
So there was four sold  online
and it may be a case that I  need
to see what was sold in 2012.
So I'll untick 2014/17.
Select that.
So I know there were two items
sold in those countries online.
And in that year.
Again, if I just highlighted the
first country and then went to the
sort and filter, if I untick that
it would remove all of the filters
from the column headings, and then
your data is all back to normal.